# NAVEEN N RAVICHANDRASEKARAN

250 East 6th Street, Apt 0402 \$\infty\$ Saint Paul, MN 55101 (832) \$\cdot 720 \cdot 2393 \$\infty\$ nravi.research@gmail.com

### **SUMMARY**

Professional Software Engineer with experience in the general areas of parallel and distributed computing. Specifically, my technical skills focuses in the following areas: (i) parallel programming models and runtime systems (MPI and PGAS models like OpenSHMEM, Global Arrays, and Coarray Fortran); (ii) parallel computing architectures, and (iii) high-speed interconnects

#### **EXPERIENCE**

# Hewlett Packard Enterprise

01/01/2020 - present

Systems/Software Engineer - Programming Environment Message Passing Toolkit Saint Paul, MN Cray, Inc 12/26/2015 - 12/12/2019

Software Engineer - Programming Environment Message Passing Toolkit

Saint Paul, MN

- · HPC and parallel programming runtime optimizations for HPE/CrayHPE/Cray supercomputer and cluster hardware to be utilized by specific customers like U.S government and commercial petroleum industries
- · Work specifically on Cray software stacks like Cray MPICH, Cray SHMEM, and Global Arrays
- · Participate and represent HPE/Cray in OpenSHMEM standards committee

Cray, Inc

05/18/2015 - 12/25/2015

Intern - Programming Environment Message Passing Toolkit

Saint Paul. MN

- · Research, Prototype, and Implement new features in Cray SHMEM programming library
- · Optimize Global Arrays library for NAMD and NWChem Chemistry applications

### University of Houston

09/14/2013 - 05/15/2015

Research Assistant - HPC Tools

Houston, TX

- · Research Assistant to Dr.Barbara Chapman(Chair, Computer Science & Mathematics(CSM) Group Brookhaven National Laboratory)
- · Research and explore strategies for runtime optimizations, and compiler-tools interactions for large-scale parallel systems using OpenSHMEM and Coarray Fortran programming models

### Cognizant Technology Solutions

06/23/2011 - 07/12/2013

Programmer Analyst

Chennai, India

· Prepare parallel test framework to validate bank statements for one of the leading financial services company in their Asset Services Project

### KEY ACTIVITIES

1. OpenSHMEM standardization Effort, Participate and represent HPE in OpenSHMEM standards committee. http://openshmem.org/.

#### **EDUCATION**

# University of Houston, Main Campus

December 2015

M.S. in Computer Science - Specialization in Parallel & Distributed Systems

Anna University, India

May 2011

Bachelors in Engineering - Electrical & Electronics Engineering

#### TECHNICAL STRENGTHS

**Programming Languages** C/C++, Fortran, Python

Parallel Programming Models OpenSHMEM, MPI, Coarray Fortran, OpenMP

Network Libraries DMAPP, Verbs, Libfabric System Architectures Aarch64, x86\_64, GPU

Architectures Cray Supercomputers, & Clusters, Intel MIC

## AWARDS AND ACCOMPLISHMENTS

1. Best Paper Award, 8th International Conference on Partitioned Global Address Space Programming Model(PGAS 2014).

- 2. Graduate Assistant Tution Fellowship, September 2013 May 2015.
- 3. Best Undergraduate Student Project, Mepco Schlenk Eng. College, Anna University, India, 2011.

#### **PROJECTS**

# **Current Projects**

### 1. Cray OpenSHMEMX

- Cray OpenSHMEMX, a new OpenSHMEM library implementation that supersedes the existing production ready Cray SHMEM library on future exascale Cray Shasta architectures
- Design and develop Cray OpenSHMEMX from scratch with support for different transport layers including DMAPP, XPMEM, and Libfabric

### 2. Cray MPICH

- Create an optimized message matching layer for the MPI implementation
- Optimize GPU-awareness in the MPI implementation

### **Past Projects**

### 1. Cray SHMEM

**Project description:** Cray SHMEM is a production quality SHMEM implementation on different Cray platforms with OpenSHMEM standards compliant. **My Contributions:** I am particularly involved in maintaining library along with implementing new features as per the OpenSHMEM standards, also propose and prototype new features like Communication Contexts, Symmetric Memory Partitions and Teams(PE-Subsets).

### 2. Cray Global Arrays(Cray-GA) ComEx-DMAPP

**Project description:** Global Arrays is a PGAS library from Pacific Northwest National Laboratory (PNNL). **My Contributions:** I was involved in optimizing and maintain the ComEx - DMAPP communication layer.

### 3. OpenSHMEM Reference Implementation

**Project description:** University of Houston worked with *Oak Ridge National Laboratory* to standardize OpenSHMEM via a community-driven specification with a reference implementation. **My Contributions:** I have been particularly involved in the optimization of the collective communication performance.

### 4. Coarray Fortran

**Project description:** Coarray Fortran is a set of new language features incorporated into the Fortran 2008 standard to enable parallel programming in Fortran with minimal changes to the

language syntax. It is a joint project between University of Houston and *Total* My Contributions: I was particularly involved in the optimization of the Coarray Fortran runtime library with new underlying communication layers.

### REFEREED CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOP PUBLICATIONS

My full name is **Naveen Namashivayam Ravichandrasekaran** and I author all conference and workshop publications as **Naveen Namashivayam**.

- N.Namashivayam, S.Mehta, and P.C.Yew. "Variable-sized Blocks for Locality-aware SpMV".
   In Proceedings of International Symposium on Code Generation and Optimization (CGO 2021).
   (Accepted).
- 2. **N.Namashivayam**, B.Long, D.Eachempati, B.Cernohous, and M.Pagel. "A Modern Fortran Interface in OpenSHMEM.". In Proceedings of ACM Transactions on Parallel Computing, August, 2020.
- 3. N.Namashivayam, B.Cernohous, D.Pou, and M.Pagel. "Introducing Cray OpenSHMEMX A Modular Multi-Communication Layer OpenSHMEM Implementation.". In Proceedings of Fifth Workshop on OpenSHMEM and Related Technologies, August, 2018, Hanover, USA.
- 4. **N.Namashivayam**, B.Cernohous, K.Kandalla, D.Pou, J.Robichaux, J.Dinan, and M.Pagel. "Symmetric Memory Partitions in OpenSHMEM: A case study with Intel KNL". In Proceedings of Fourth Workshop on OpenSHMEM and Related Technologies: Big Compute and Big Data Convergence, August, 2017, Annapolis, USA.
- 5. K.Kandalla, P.Mendygral, N.Radcliffe, B.Cernohous, **N.Namashivayam**, K.McMahon, C.Sadlo and M.Pagel "Current State of the Cray MPT Software Stacks on the Cray XC Series Supercomputers". In proceedings of Cray User Group Meeting, 2017, Redmond, USA.
- 6. **N.Namashivayam**, D.Knaak, B.Cernohous, N.Radcliffe, and M.Pagel. "An Evaluation of Thread-Safe and Contexts-Domains Features in Cray SHMEM". In Proceedings of Third Workshop on OpenSHMEM and Related Technologies: Enhancing OpenSHMEM for Hybrid Environments, August, 2016, Hanover, USA.
- 7. N.Namashivayam, D.Eachempati, D.Khaldi and B.Chapman. "OpenSHMEM as a Portable Communication Layer for PGAS Models A Case Study with Coarray Fortran". In Proceedings of IEEE Cluster 2015, September, 2015, Chicago, USA.
- 8. N.Namashivayam, D.Khaldi, D.Eachempati and B.Chapman. "Extending the Strided Communication Interface in OpenSHMEM". In Proceedings of Second OpenSHMEM Workshop: Experiences, Implementations and Tools, August, 2015, Annapolis, USA.
- 9. D.Knaak, and **N.Namashivayam**. "Proposing OpenSHMEM Extensions Towards a Future for Hybrid Programming and Heterogeneous Computing", In Proceedings of Second OpenSHMEM Workshop: Experiences, Implementations and Tools, August, 2015, Annapolis, USA.
- 10. **N.Namashivayam**, S.Ghosh, D.Khaldi, D.Eachempati, and B.Chapman. "Native Mode-Based Optimizations of Remote Memory Accesses in OpenSHMEM for Intel Xeon Phi", 8th International Conference on Partitioned Global Address Space Programming Models (PGAS 2014).

### **THESIS**

• N.Namashivayam. "OpenSHMEM as an Effective Communication Layer for PGAS Models". Master's Thesis, University of Houston, October, 2015.